Southern New England Telephone Company Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Series V: Studies, Reports and Plans ( undated, 1911-1985 ) is organized alphabetically by title of the document, department or subject. There are mid-year and year-end reports from (1975-86) for Data and Information Systems; reports and studies pertaining to directory assistance charging issues, 1973-78; earnings and profit studies; a series of reports filed with the PUCA/DPUC, 1975-79; and other individual documents. The series also includes a collection of project reports, ranging from 1965 to the mid-1980s, available on microfiche. The material is organized first by microfilming project number and then alphabetical by acronym. Whenever available the meaning of the acronym is spelled out.
Series V: Studies, Reports and Plans.
Series VI: Subject Files ( undated, 1879-2003 ) is arranged alphabetically. The basis for this series was a set of files kept by the company as “history files.” Much of the material was gathered or created during the writing of a company history, Connecticut Pioneers in Telephony, by J. Leigh Walsh, published in 1950 (Dodd Call No. C 5356). The series contains materials such as files on exchange histories and facts, personal recollections, buildings, storms and disaster, and key figures in SNET history. Of particular interest in this series are files of town histories. These files often contain material of a general historical nature, as well as material associated with the telephone.
Series VI: Subject Files.
Series VII: Publications ( undated, 1878-1998 ) is arranged in three sub-series: Clippings, Material Produced by SNET, and Material Produced by Others. The series also contains a listing of SNET Periodicals for reference purposes. The Clippings sub-series contains newspaper clippings in scrapbook form dating from 1899 to 1997. Other clippings are from various newspapers throughout Connecticut and the region that pertain to SNET and telephone company issues. Of note is one large folder dedicated to the 1936 flood. The earlier scrapbooks are very fragile. The sub-series, Material Produced by SNET, is arranged alphabetically. It consists of bill inserts, pamphlets, booklets, and guides to service, all of which cover a wide variety of topics. The Material Produced by Others sub-series is also arranged alphabetically by title. It contains booklets, journals, pamphlets, guides, almanacs, magazines, and reports primarily published by ATT or the Bell System. The Periodicals have been pulled from the collection. They are listed for reference purposes and are cataloged in the university on-line system. It is arranged alphabetically by title in seven sections: an A to Z Titles List, Periodicals, Oversized Periodicals, Bound Periodicals, Oversized Bound Periodicals, Directories, and Bound Directories. The sections contain materials in different sizes and formats. Some titles changed formats and are listed in more than one section. The A to Z List directs the user to the various sections for each title. The Periodicals and Oversized Periodicals sections consist of SNET publications such as: newsletters, news briefs, magazines, bulletins, newspapers, guides, and directories. These materials are in folders that are boxed, numbered 1 through 6. The Directories section contains exchange directories produced for Connecticut that cover cities, towns and the whole state with Connecticut Statewide Directories. The section also lists directories produced by Predecessor and Subsidiary companies. Of interest is the only known copy of the first directory ever printed in the world from New Haven in 1878. There are also Official Directories of SNET departments, divisions, and employees and directories for Retired Employees. These materials are also in folders and boxes numbered 7 and 8. The Bound Periodicals, Oversized Bound Periodicals and Bound Directories are stored on shelves and are listed alphabetically and by year. They cover various SNET topics such as sales or news and the Bound Directories are “Phone Books” that show telephone numbers for many cities or towns and the whole state over a large span of years.
Series VII: Publications.
Series VIII: Predecessor and Subsidiary Companies ( undated, 1878-1979 ) contains the records of those companies that have preceded or been absorbed by the Southern New England Telephone Company. The series is arranged according to a volume numbering system set up by the company. The series is comprised of two sub-series, Predecessor Companies and Subsidiary Companies. The sub-series Predecessor Companies contains the records of the District Telephone Company of New Haven, the Connecticut District Telephone Company, the District Telephone and Automatic Signal Company, and the Connecticut Telephone Company. The sub-series Subsidiary Companies includes the records of the Connecticut River Telegraph Company, the Connecticut Telegraph Company, the Naugatuck Telephone Company, the New London Telephone Company, the Stamford and Norwalk Telephone Company, the Interstate Telephone Company, the Ansonia Telephone Company, the Standard Time and Electric Company, the Windham County Telephone Company, the Fishers Island Telegraph Company, the Connecticut Electric Light Company, the New Britain Telephone Company, the Canaan Local Telephone Company, the Farmington Valley Telephone Company, the Sharon Telephone Company, the Waterbury Automatic Telephone Company, and the Woodbury Telephone Company. Most record groups contain minutes and incorporation material. Material such as journals, ledgers, financial data, and tax material are included with some.
Series VIII: Predecessor and Subsidiary Companies.
Series IX: Memorabilia, Artifacts and Artwork ( undated, 1904-1990s ) contains a wide variety of artifactual material such as: equipment, employee awards, commemorative material, general company memorabilia, promotional material, framed artwork, posters, scrapbooks, and a few miscellaneous maps. Although there is an attempt to organize the material there is no specific order. Of particular interest in this series is the scrapbook of E.B. Baker, a key figure in the early development of the company, and the minute book of the 1880 National Telephone Exchange Association Convention held in Niagara, New York.
Series IX: Memorabilia, Artifacts and Artwork.
Series X: Audio/Visual ( undated, 1951-2003 ) has eleven subseries arranged by format. The subseries are Cassette Tapes; Reel to Reel Audio Tapes (5 inch); Reel to Reel Audio Tapes (7inch); Record Albums (33 1/3 RPM); Video VHS; Beta (1 inch); Beta (3/4 inch); 16 Millimeter Sound On Film (3 inch reels); 16 Millimeter Sound On Film (5 inch reels); Microfilm 35 Millimeter and Microfilm 16 Millimeter. The subseries' organizations are alphabetical, except the microfilms, which follow SNET's original reel number order. The SNET Audio Visual Department, external production services, radio and television stations produced the materials in this series. It contains no documentation.
The Cassette Tapes cover such topics as meetings, commercials, employee information programs, interviews of SNET employees, public information programs, press conferences and other various topics pertaining to the communications industry. The recordings occurred from the early 1970s to 1982. The Reel to Reel subseries grouping is by 5 and 7 inch reel. The medium is reel-to-reel audiotape. The 5 inch topics are primarily SNET commercial recordings with some telephone related subjects and the 7 inch tapes are recordings of radio talk shows, speeches or press conferences. The time frame is 1970 to 1981. The Record Albums are Master Recordings of SNET commercials or topics on 33 1/3 vinyl disks from 1951 to 1965. The Video VHS tapes cover various SNET topics or programs such as public relations and SNET history from the early 1980s to 2003. The two Beta subseries are recordings on ⅓34; inch and 1 inch Beta tape also covering various topics from SNET and ATT in the early 1970s to 1990. The two 16 Millimeter Sound On Film subseries are also on two different sized reels, 3 and 5 inches. The films are SNET commercials with synchronized audio from 1964 to 1980. The Microfilm subseries consist of 35 and 16 millimeter microfilm organized by original SNET reel numbers. The dates listed are when the materials were microfilmed. The topics are Executive, Financial and Accounting related covering areas such as deeds, contracts, leases and meeting minutes from the early 1900s to 1980.
The materials in the Reel to Reel, Record Album, Beta and 16 Millimeter Sound On Film subseries are very fragile and require special equipment, careful handling and staff supervision for use. The equipment needed includes a reel-to-reel tape deck, 33 1/3 record player, Beta tape player and 16mm projector and screen respectively.
Series X: Audio/Visual.
Series XI: Photographs ( undated, 1878-1998 ) has eleven subseries: Contemporary, Contemporary Oversized, Transparencies, Contact Sheets, Contact Sheets Oversized, Historical, Historical Oversized, Historical Oversized Fragile, Historical Fragile, Slides and Negatives. The SNET departments Creative Services, General Information and Public Relations took the majority of the photographs. In other cases, SNET utilized independent photographers or studios and the services of ATT. There is very little documentation that accompanies the photographs although many have captions, headings, descriptions, SNET job numbers and location or date information.
The Contemporary subseries organization is in SNET's original alphabetical order by subject heading. The time frame spans from the 1930s to 1998. The subseries contains mostly 3 by 5, 4 by 6 and 8 by 10 print photographs enclosed in clear protective sheets and grouped by subject in folders. When readily available, dates are provided in the inventory list. Many items have information written on the back such as the date, location, subject and SNET job number. The job number can be cross-referenced to the contact sheets and/or negatives to obtain more information. The photographs cover a wide range of topics pertaining to SNET and Connecticut such as: meetings, groups, building, cities and towns, equipment, scenic areas, disasters, personnel, political figures, plant construction, operators, switchboards, SNET workers and telephones. The company used the photographs in advertisements, ceremonies, displays, promotions and company publications. The Contemporary Oversized materials are larger photographs or scrapbooks grouped alphabetically and by size.
The Transparency subseries arrangement remains in the original SNET order by transparency or “TR” number followed by a general heading. Other transparencies are grouped by subject. SNET used the materials for publication covers or advertisements. The Contact Sheets are organized first in ledgers by year, then boxed and foldered by SNET job number and corresponding dates. Freelance studios and topical contact sheets are included in the subseries. The sheets are rough prints of negatives and often give important information not found in the regular photographs. The Oversized section is organized by subject.
The Historical subseries are older SNET photographs from 1878 to the 1930s. However, some folders contain images of operators into the 1970s. The materials are also in protective sheets and folders organized in SNET's original alphabetical order by subject heading. They cover topics similar to the Contemporary photographs. The Historical Oversized materials contain larger photographs and scrapbooks boxed by size. The Historical Oversized Fragile materials are larger images requiring careful handling. They are mostly supported with backing boards. The Historical Fragile Restricted photographs are older, very sensitive materials in four flap enclosures that require staff supervision for access and use. Most of the photographs in all the historical sections are singular images with no negatives or copies and should be handled with extreme care. The Slides are arranged topically in trays and cover a variety of SNET topics and presentations. The Negatives 35 Millimeter Film subseries is filed by the SNET job number that corresponds to many of the Contemporary prints and the Contact Sheets.
Series XI: Photographs.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut businesses. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Going Beyond the Call 1997-0122.vr1
Bibliography
Reuel E. Benson, Jr.. The First Century of the Telephone in Connecticut., Illustrated by George De Costa. New Haven: SNET, 1978.
Allerton Frank Brooks. “Giving Wings to Words” Connecticut Origins of Modern Telephony, 1878-1953., New York: Newcomen Society in North America, 1953.
Victor Morris Tyler. A Short Review of Connecticut Telephony, 1878-1907., New Haven, 1957.
J. Leigh Walsh. Connecticut Pioneers in Telephony: The Origins and Growth of the Telephone Industry in Connecticut, New Haven: Morris F. Tyler Chapter, Telephone Pioneers of America, 1950.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Books.; Manuscripts.; Notebooks.; Publications.; Photographs.; Blueprints.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Videocassettes.; Audio cassettes.; Audio visual materials.; Memorabilia.; Artwork.; Advertising Records.
Occupations:
Communications Company
Restrictions on Access
All materials less than 20 years old will be restricted.
All proprietary material will be restricted 26 years.
All personnel material will be restricted for a period of 75 years after the date of creation of the records with the following
exceptions:
a. The individual named in the personal information, or their legal representative, if a signed release is provided to A&SC
b. Official representatives of SNET if such a representative provides a signed request from (name of SNET officer) on corporate letterhead.
Custodial History
Southern New England Telecommunications Corporation was the owner of the records prior to transfer of ownership.
Acquisition Information
SBC SNET donated the collection in July 2002.
Detailed Description
- Series X: Audio/Visual, undated, 1951-1998
  - Cassette Tapes
    - ATT Annual Meeting, 1976 March (Box 357)
    - Annual Meeting SNET (2), 1977
    - Clio Awards, undated
    - Commercials
      - ATT Reach Out (2), 1978
      - Bell System Business, undated
      - Bell System Long Distance, 1975
      - Northwestern Bell, Bellboy, undated
      - Northwestern Bell Directory Assistance, undated
      - Pacific Telephone Long Distance, 1975
      - SNET
        - Answers, Coins, undated
        - Christmas, undated
        - Clio Award Touch Tone, 1976
        - Coins, undated
        - Design Line, undated
        - Directory Assistance, 1976
        - Directory Assistance Revised, 1976
        - Directory Assistance What City?, undated
        - Directory Assistance What City?, 1977
        - Extension, 1975
        - Extension, undated
        - Family, 1976
        - Long Distance Business, undated
        - Long Distance Coins, undated
        - Long Distance Hilltops, Family, undated
        - Long Distance 48 for 89cents, 1978
        - Lovers, 1977
        - Mother's Day, 1978
        - Nathan Audition, undated
        - Samples, Design Line, undated
        - Touch-a-matic, undated
        - You Made My Day, undated
    - Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Concert Celebration, undated
    - Employee Information SNET
      - Backs At Work, 1983
      - Back Help, 1983
      - Executive Program #'s 1-6, undated
      - Executive Program #'s 7-12, undated (Box 358)
      - Executive Program #'s 1-8, 11, 12, undated
    - Hartford, undated
    - Interviews
      - Burchard and Hyde (3), 1976
      - Concelmo, 1977
      - Corves (3), 1976
      - Coughlin, 1977
      - Donofrio, 1981
      - Donofrio, undated
      - Ekstrom and Avery, 1977
      - Ekstrom, 1977
      - Gradwell, 1976
      - Johnson and Aleksa, 1976
      - Little, 1976
      - Little and Hermes, 1977
      - Lombardi and Zuboff, 1976
      - Makula, 1976
      - Miglio, 1976
      - Miglio, 1976
      - Operators (2), 1978
      - Owens, 1976
      - Schneider, 1974 (Box 359)
      - Tinker and Gorden, 1976
      - Van Sinderen, 1976
      - Van Sinderen (2), 1977
      - Zypka, 1976
    - Identification Focus Group, 1985
    - Party Line, 1977
    - Public Information
      - From Rhetoric To Action Program
        - Speakers (5), 1991
        - Education (12), 1991
    - SONECOR Information (2), undated
    - Stamford, undated
    - Van Sinderen, Alfred W.
      - Press Conference, 1982
      - Press Conference, 1982
      - Press Conference/Luncheon (3), 1977
      - Press Conference/Luncheon (3), 1977
      - Press Luncheon (2), 1974
      - Press Luncheon, 1974
      - Press Luncheon, 1974
      - Speeches
        - Backgrounder, 1982 March
        - Economic Development, 1977 January
        - Hartford Rotary Club, 1974 August
        - Meriden Rotary Club, 1976 November (Box 360)
        - New Haven Rotary Club (2), 1976 June
        - WADS, Ansonia, 1977 April
      - Questions And Answers (2), undated
    - Yellow Pages Story (2), 1976 July
    - Watson, Thomas A. describes telephone invention, 1976
    - Werwaiss, Speech-Rate Case, 1977 May
  - Reel to Reel Audio Tapes, (5 inch)
    - Commercials (Box 361)
      - ATT, multiple titles, undated
      - SNET
        - Be Choosey, 1978
        - Cinemix, 1981
        - Convenience and Huff-n-puff, 1975
        - Convenience and Huff-n-puff, 1975
        - Convenience (Rev3) Huff-n-puff (Rev6), undated
        - Decotel, 1972
        - Decotel Phone, 1972
        - Decotel (2), 1973
        - Decotel Extension Phones, 1972
        - Decotel and Selling Brands, 1973
        - Decotel and Extension Convenience (2), 1973
        - Decotel and Trimline (2), 1974
        - Deco Trimline and Cuddlephone, 1974
        - Designline, 1976
        - Doctor and Smart Talk, undated
        - Extension Phone (2), 1971
        - Extension Phone-Girl, 1973
        - Extension Phone-Girl (2), 1974
        - Fall Campaign- Extension, 1973
        - Footsteps, Slow Down and Thanks (2), 1976
        - Get Together by Long Distance (2), 1976
        - Gift General Radio, 1979
        - Gift General Radio, undated
        - Home Improvement Phones (2), 1977
        - Keep In Touch (2), 1977
        - Keep Mottos and Vaudeville (3), 1974 (Box 362)
        - Long Distance Calling-Mother's Day, undated
        - Lovers (2), 1977
        - Mother's Day (5), 1973-1978
        - Mother's Day-Be Choosey, 1978
        - Music Phones and Christmas Voices, 1974
        - News About Long Distance Rates, undated
        - New Extension Spot, 1973
        - Ooh's and Ahh's of Christmas, 1977
        - SNET (4 cuts), undated
        - Soul Decotel (2), 1973
        - Styles and Colors, 1973
        - Sunday and Various Topics, 1975
        - Typewriter and Business Trip, 1976
        - Vacationers (2), 1977
        - Vignettes and Referee (2), 1976
        - Visitors, Right Time and Price Conscious, 1976
        - What City Please? (2), 1976
        - What City Please? (2), 1977
        - Who Do You Know? (2), 1977
        - Who Do You Know? Rates, undated
        - Window Washer, undated
        - WOAS (World on a String) Extension, 1971
        - WOAS Extension, 1971 (Box 363)
        - WOAS Extension (2), 1972
        - Written Number and Long Distance, 1975
        - You Made My Day (2), 1977
        - $10.3 Call (2), 1977
        - “48 for 89cents”, 1978
        - “48 for 89cents” (2), undated
    - Topics (Box 364)
      - Centennial and Long Distance, 1975
      - Centennial Material, 1976
      - Thomas A. Watson, 1976
      - 40th Anniversary of dialogue on film, undated
  - Reel to Reel Audio Tapes, (7 inch)
    - Burchard and Hyde RSVP (WELI Radio Talk Show) (3), 1976 (Box 365)
    - Governor John Dempsey RSVP (3), 1972
    - Van Sinderen, A.W.
      - Competition, 1974
      - Press Conference, 1976
      - RSVP (5), 1972
      - RSVP (2), 1973
      - Speech, New Haven Rotary Club, 1976
  - Record Albums (33 1/3 RPM)
    - Commercials (SNET) (Box 366)
      - Additional Telephones, undated
      - Be A Friend, 1957
      - Call Me, undated
      - Call Out of Town By Number, 1951
      - Christmas Promotion, 1955
      - Direct Distance Dialing, undated
      - Extension
        - Three Blind Mice, undated
        - Sportscaster, Cellar, Upstairs (2), undated
      - Handy Phone (2), 1960
      - It's A Snap, 1965
      - Long Distance (2), 1961
      - Long Distance (2), 1962
      - Long Distance (2), 1963
      - Long Distance, Fall, 1963
      - Princess Telephone (2), 1960
      - Yellow Pages Campaign, 1961
    - Concert and Weekly Bell Telephone Spot, 1956
    - The Importance of Telephone People, undated
  - Video VHS (Box 367)
    - Black and White Footage of Old Telephones, undated
    - Corporate Advertisement “You Know SNET”, 1989
    - Corporate ID “We Are SNET”, 1991
    - From Rhetoric to Action Program
      - Connecticut Officials, undated
      - Governor Roy Romer of Colorado, undated
      - Mary Hatwood Futrell, undated
    - “Going Beyond the Call” A History of SNET (2), 1998
    - I-SNET Connecticut's Information Superhighway (2), 1994
    - Management Tool Kit and Standards of Conduct, 1997
    - Restoring Service “Teamwork and Technology” (Hurricane Bob), 1991
    - SNET Info Minutes, undated
    - SNET Through the Years: “We did a lot together!”, 1995 (Box 368)
    - Still the Oldest and Still the Best: SBC SNET 125th Anniversary Commemorative, 2003
    - “Vietnam: A Chance To Understand” short version (2), undated
    - “Vietnam: A Chance To Understand” long version (2), undated
  - Beta, (1 inch)
    - ATT Newsbreak, 1983 February (Box 369)
    - Concert Celebration Martin Luther King Jr., undated
    - “Happy Faces” SNET TV Show, undated
    - The Past is Prologue Centennial, 1972 March
    - SNET 1980 In Review, 1981 April
    - Stamford Classic Road Race, 1986 April
    - St. Gaudiens, undated
    - The New SNET, 1993 May; note: BETACAM Metal Tape
  - Beta, (3/4 inch)
    - Against The Wind Tornado Restoration, 1989 July (Box 370)
    - ATT Annual Meeting, 1976
    - Business Spots SNET, 1987
    - Corporate Advertising and the GHO, 1986 July
    - CPTV SNET Historic, 1989 March
    - Connecticut's 350th Anniversary, 1986 April
    - The Dream Lives On Concert Promo, 1986 February
    - Field Footage Meriden, 1986 December
    - GHO and Channel 3 SNET Portable Phone, 1986 (Box 371)
    - Introducing the Business Division, 1981 February
    - Lightnet Press Conference, 1983 August
    - Marathon Classic Stamford, CT, 1986 April
    - New Sonecor Network Business Commercials, 1985 June
    - ODC Management Intro, Values, 1987
    - OLIN HQ Fire, 1981, 1988
    - Reach Out for Health Intro, 1983 March
    - Recycling, 1990 September (Box 372)
    - Sonecor Sees the Future, 1986 March
    - Teacher Recognition, undated
    - Video Clips: TV Media and Advertising, 1986 January
    - Window Dubs
      - 1-3, 1983 January
      - 4-6, 1983 January
      - 6-9, 1983 January
      - 9-12, 1983 January
      - 13-15, 1983 January
  - 16 Millimeter Sound On Film, (3 inch reels)
    - Commercials
      - Altone Phone, undated (Box 373)
      - Animated Dial (2), undated
      - Astro (2), undated
      - Automation Industries (3), 1975 October
      - Baby (2), 1969 November
      - Bakery (2), 1974 May
      - Baseball (2), undated
      - Basement (2), [1966?] (Box 374)
      - Bedroom (2), 1966
      - Bell System, The, 1978